About UCanAccess

This is the home page of UCanAccess, an open-source Java JDBC driver implementation that allows Java developers and JDBC client programs (e.g., DBeaver, NetBeans, SQLeo, OpenOffice Base, LibreOffice Base, Squirrel SQL) to read/write Microsoft Access databases.

Because it is a pure Java implementation it runs on both Windows and non-Windows operating systems (e.g., Linux/Unix). No ODBC needed. UCanAccess uses:

Jackcess as Microsoft Access input/output library (link: https://github.com/spannm/jackcess/)
HSQLDB (aka HyperSQL) as synchronized DBMS (link: http://hsqldb.org/)

Features

Supported Access formats: 2000, 2002/2003, 2007, 2010/2013/2016 databases. (Access 97 format supported for read-only)
SELECT, INSERT, UPDATE, DELETE statements. Transactions and savepoints.
Access data types: YESNO, BYTE, INTEGER, LONG, SINGLE, DOUBLE, NUMERIC, CURRENCY, COUNTER, TEXT, OLE, MEMO, GUID, DATETIME.
Concurrent access from multiple application server threads.
Connection pooling.
ANSI 92 SQL, core SQL-2008.
Access SQL.
Core built-in functions for Access SQL are supported (e.g., Date(), Now(), IIf(), ...).
You can execute Select queries defined and saved in Access. Since version 1.0.1, UCanAccess can execute Crosstab queries (TRANSFORM ... PIVOT ...)
LIKE operator accepts both standard % and Access-specific * as multi-character wildcards, both standard _ and Access-specific ? as single-character wildcards, # for single digit and [xxx][!xxx] for character intervals (Access).
Both & and + (Access SQL) as well as || (ANSI SQL) for string concatenation.
Square brackets for field names, table names and view names (saved Access queries) that include spaces or other special characters, e.g., SELECT [my column] FROM [my table].
Access date format (e.g., #11/22/2003 10:42:58 PM#).
Both double quote " and single quote ' as SQL string delimiters.
Read and write support to complex types (i.e., array of Version, Attachment, SingleValue).
Since version 2.0.1, UCanAccess supports both constants and functions as default column values in CREATE TABLE statements e.g. CREATE TABLE tbl (fld1 TEXT PRIMARY KEY, fld2 LONG DEFAULT 3 NOT NULL, fld3 TEXT(255) NOT NULL, fld4 DATETIME DEFAULT Now(), fld5 TEXT DEFAULT 'bla')
Command-line console ("console.bat" and "console.sh"). You can run SQL commands and display their results. CSV export command included.

Limitations

Access data macros are not supported. UCanAccess can update tables for which event-driven data macros are defined, but the macros themselves are ignored.
In versions prior to UCanAccess 4.0.0, only basic DDL was supported (CREATE TABLE with Primary Key, DROP TABLE).
Since version 4.0.0 UCanAccess can now support DDL for Table metadata modification:

Columns, Primary Keys and other Indexes can now be added to an existing table.
UCanAccess 4.x.x has also the ability to create Foreign Keys and to rename Tables.

Very limited multiprocess access support (details here). Nevertheless, it tries to synchronize data when a concurrent process modifies the Access database file.

Requirements

From version 5.1.0 UCanAccess requires Java 11 or later to run.
From version 5.0.0 Java 8 or later is required, while older versions require at least Java 6.

When dealing with large databases and using the default "memory" setting (i.e., with driver property memory=true), it is recommended that users allocate sufficient memory to the JVM using the -Xms and -Xmx options.
Otherwise it will be necessary to set the driver's "memory" property to "false":

Connection conn = DriverManager.getConnection("jdbc:ucanaccess://c:/data/myaccessdb.mdb;memory=false");

Note: If you're working with especially large files or in memory-constrained environments, and performance with memory=false is not acceptable, consider using the Jackcess library directly for low-level access. This bypasses the in-memory HSQLDB layer and can significantly reduce memory usage while improving performance.

Dependencies

UCanAccess depends on Jackcess and HSQLDB. If you are using Apache Maven to manage your dependencies (recommended) simply add the following to your pom.xml:

<dependency>
    <groupId>io.github.spannm</groupId>
    <artifactId>ucanaccess</artifactId>
    <version>5.1.3</version>
</dependency>

Maven will add the other dependencies for you. If you are manually managing your classpath, you will need to add the ucanaccess-5.2.0.jar file along with its dependencies to your classpath.

In order to open encrypted files you must use UCanAccess 2.x.x or later with jackcess-encrypt-2.x.x and all related dependencies. Again, if you are using Maven, simply add this extra dependency:

<dependency>
    <groupId>com.healthmarketscience.jackcess</groupId>
    <artifactId>jackcess-encrypt</artifactId>
    <version>4.0.2</version>
</dependency>

Getting Started

Note that the distribution comes with a large number of JUnit test cases which illustrate how UCanAccess may be used.

Adding UCanAccess to your Java project

If your project uses Maven you can simply include UCanAccess via the following dependency in your Maven POM:

<dependency>
    <groupId>io.github.spannm</groupId>
    <artifactId>ucanaccess</artifactId>
    <version>5.1.0</version>
</dependency>

Otherwise, see this Stack Overflow answer for details on how to configure your Java project.

Establishing a UCanAccess connection

Class.forName("net.ucanaccess.jdbc.UcanaccessDriver");
Connection connTemplate = DriverManager.getConnection("jdbc:ucanaccess://<mdb or accdb file path>", user, password);

// for example:
Connection connExample = DriverManager.getConnection("jdbc:ucanaccess://c:/data/myaccessdb.mdb;memory=true");

Connection Properties

memory: set if HSQLDB will store its backing database only in memory. Default is memory=true .

lobScale: to optimize memory occupation when a relevant percent of memory occupation is for OLE (BLOB) data. This may also allow, in many cases, to use the memory=true setting, whilst it was impossible before. It should be set to a value close to the average size of OLE instances. According with the HSQLDB documentation, the values allowed are 1, 2, 4, 8, 16, 32 (the unit is Kb). Default is 2 if memory=true, 32 (HSQLDB default) otherwise.

skipIndexes: in order to minimize memory occupation, it allows skipping the creation of simple (untied to contraints) indexes. It doesn't have effect on referential integrity constraints (i.e., Index Unique, Foreign Key or Primary Key).

newDatabaseVersion: UCanAccess will create a new Access database file in the specified version if this parameter is set and the file specified in the JDBC connection URL does not exist. Valid values for this parameter are: V2000, V2003, V2007, V2010.

openExclusive (replaces the deprecated lockMdb): if openExclusive is enabled ( openExclusive=true ), UCanAccess locks the mdb/accdb file to prevent updates from other processes. Default=false.

showSchema: if true, catalog "PUBLIC" and schema "PUBLIC" and other HSQLDB schemas are shown in the DatabaseMetadata implementation. Default=false. Using showSchema=true is recommended with Squirrel SQL.

inactivityTimeout (since UcanAccess 0.1.1): it is used only with the default memory mode (memory=true). If there are no active connections for the inactivityTimeout period (in minutes) HSQLDB will be temporarily shut down and any file system resources will be released. It will be restarted at the next connection. Setting inactivityTimeout=0 can be used for avoiding this behavior. Default = 2 minutes.

immediatelyReleaseResources (replaces singleConnection which has been deprecated since UCanAccess 3.0.6): it is used for for ETL jobs, scheduled tasks, or "one-shot" use of UCanAccess with only one connection open. All resources (memory and file system) will be released at the closing of the connection. Default=false.

encrypt: it allows HSQLDB files encryption. You can use it in conjunction with memory=false. Default=false.

sysSchema: if true the Access system tables will be loaded in the "sys" readonly schema. Default=false.

ignoreCase: Disables (ignoreCase=true) or enables (ignoreCase=false) the case sensitivity of text comparison. Default is true.
For example:
Connection conn = DriverManager.getConnection("jdbc:ucanaccess://c:/data/myaccessdb.mdb;openExclusive=true;ignoreCase=true");

remap: it allows to remap the paths to one or more external linked databases.
The syntax is:
jdbc:ucanaccess://c:/data/<main db>;remap=<original db1 path>|<new db1 path>&<original i-db path>|<new i-db path>
e.g.,
jdbc:ucanaccess://c:/data/main.mdb;remap=c:\db\linkee1.mdb|C:\pluto\linkee1.mdb&c:\db\linkee2.mdb|C:\pluto\linkee2.mdb
Original path and new path must be separated by '|', different pairs must be separated by '&'.

mirrorFolder: it allows users to set the directory in which the mirror db will be created.
It forces memory=false.
Simply use mirrorFolder=java.io.tmpdir in order to specify the system temp folder for that.

keepMirror: keeps the HSQLDB mirror database after the VM ends so it can be reused by subsequent VM processes.
It forces memory=false.
In other words, using this parameter, the time-expensive process of creating and populating the database hsqldb (with memory=false), is executed only once.
jdbc:ucanaccess://c:/data/main.mdb;keepMirror=c:/data/mirrorName
Reusing the same keepMirror setting (e.g. keepMirror=c:/data/mirrorName) at the next VM process execution allows you to dramatically reduce the time of first connection. It should be used only with very large databases (e.g., 1GB with many binary OLE objects) and when:

You have to change the default memory=true setting because you can't allocate sufficient JVM heap space (Xmx VM parameter).
UCanAccess takes too much time to establish the first connection (because it's populating the HSQLDB mirror database).

Caution! - If the access database is modified by a different program (so not using UCanAccess) after the HSQLDB creates the mirror database, UCanAccess recreates and repopulates the whole mirror database for avoiding unchecked misalignments.

columnOrder: use the "DISPLAY" order of columns with SELECT * statements. ("DATA" order is still the default).
jdbc:ucanaccess://c:/data/myaccessdb.mdb;columnOrder=DISPLAY
Note that once a column order has been set on the first connection to a given database, that setting will be the same for all the following connections to that database, in the whole VM life.

concatNulls: controls the behavior of all concatenation operators ( & , + , || ) with null values:
null & 'thing' -> 'thing' . (It gave null prior to version 3.0.0.)
null + 'thing' -> 'thing' . (It gave null prior to version 3.0.0.)
If you want to switch to the old behavior, you have to set the new connection property concatNulls=true .

preventReloading: optimize the reloading of db instances. If and only if you're sure that your db can be accessed by the MS Access GUI and just one JVM instance (using UCanAccess), you can use the connection parameter preventReloading=true . It avoids the data being reloaded when they aren't actually changed by the GUI.

jackcessOpener: in order to use Jackcess Encrypt extension, you can specify a class that implements the net.ucanaccess.jdbc.IJackcessOpenerInterface interface (in that case you need additional jar files in your classpath: a version of jackcess-encrypt.jar and all related dependencies).
The following example shows a custom integration with Jackcess Encrypt for opening a Money (.mny) file: Example for UCanAccess2. Notice that you must use UCanAccess 2.x.x with jackcess-encrypt-2.x.x and all related dependencies

package yourPackage.example;

//imports from Jackcess Encrypt
import com.healthmarketscience.jackcess.CryptCodecProvider;
import com.healthmarketscience.jackcess.Database;
import com.healthmarketscience.jackcess.DatabaseBuilder;
import net.ucanaccess.jdbc.IJackcessOpenerInterface;

import java.io.File;
import java.io.IOException;

public class CryptCodecOpener implements IJackcessOpenerInterface {

    public Database open(File fl, String pwd) throws IOException {
        DatabaseBuilder dbd = new DatabaseBuilder(fl);
        dbd.setAutoSync(false);
        dbd.setCodecProvider(new CryptCodecProvider(pwd));
        dbd.setReadOnly(false);
        return dbd.open();

    }

    // Notice that the parameter setting AutoSync=false is recommended with UCanAccess for performance reasons.
    // UCanAccess flushes the updates to disk at transaction end.
    // For more details about autosync parameter (and related tradeoff), see the Jackcess documentation.
}

Class.forName("net.ucanaccess.jdbc.UcanaccessDriver");
Connection conn = DriverManager.getConnection("jdbc:ucanaccess:///opt/prova1.mny;jackcessOpener=yourPackage.example.CryptCodecOpener", "sa", password);
...

For old UCanAccess versions (0.x.x, 1.x.x) JackcessOpenerInterface should be implemented in a different way, because of the jackcess API changes from jackcess1 to jackcess2.

package yourPackage.example;

import java.io.File;
import java.io.IOException;
//imports from Jackcess Encrypt
import com.healthmarketscience.jackcess.CryptCodecProvider;
import com.healthmarketscience.jackcess.Database;

import net.ucanaccess.jdbc.IJackcessOpenerInterface;

public class CryptCodecOpener implements JackcessOpenerInterface {
    public Database open(File _fl, String _pwd) throws IOException {
        return Database.open(_fl, true, true, null, null, new CryptCodecProvider(_pwd));
    }
}

Identifiers escaping

You should escaping identifiers including a blank space using square brackets or backtick character (`).
Also you shold escaping identifiers that equal a SQL keyword (e.g. SELECT * FROM [SELECT] or SELECT * FROM `SELECT`).

SQL Keywords are: ALL, AND,ANY, AS, AT, AVG, BETWEEN, BOTH, BY, CALL, CASE, CAST, COALESCE, CONSTRAINT, CORRESPONDING, CONVERT, COUNT, CREATE, CROSS, DEFAULT, DISTINCT,DO, DROP, ELSE, EVERY, EXISTS, EXCEPT, FOR, FROM, FULL, GRANT, GROUP, HAVING, IN, INNER , INTERSECT, INTO, IS, JOIN, LEFT, LEADING, LIKE, MAX , MIN, NATURAL, NOT, NULLIF, ON, ORDER, OR, OUTER, PRIMARY, REFERENCES, RIGHT, SELECT, SET, SOME, STDDEV_POP, STDDEV_SAMP, SUM, TABLE, THEN, TO, TRAILING, TRIGGER, UNION, UNIQUE, USING, USER, VALUES, VAR_POP, VAR_SAMP, WHEN, WHERE, WITH, END.

Examples

Creating tables with DDL

Statement st = conn.createStatement();
st.execute("CREATE TABLE example1 (id COUNTER PRIMARY KEY, descr TEXT(400), number NUMERIC(12,3), date0 DATETIME)");
st.execute("CREATE TABLE dkey (c COUNTER, number NUMERIC(23, 5), PRIMARY KEY (C, NUMBER)");
st.execute("CREATE TABLE dtrx (c TEXT, number NUMERIC(23, 5), UNIQUE (C, NUMBER)) ");
st.execute("CREATE TABLE Parent (x AUTOINCREMENT PRIMARY KEY, y TEXT(222))");
st.execute("CREATE TABLE Babe (k LONG, y LONG, PRIMARY KEY(k,y), FOREIGN KEY (y) REFERENCES Parent (x) )");

Also UCanAccess supports create table as (<sql select>) syntax:

st.executeUpdate("CREATE TABLE copy AS (SELECT * FROM example1) WITH DATA ");

Executing queries

The following example shows a full outer join:

Statement st = conn.createStatement();
ResultSet rs = st.executeQuery("SELECT * FROM example3 FULL OUTER JOIN example4 ON (example3.id = example4.id)");

Using Access functions

ResultSet rs1 = st.executeQuery("SELECT IIf(descr='Show must go off', 'tizio', 'caio&sempronio'&'&M A'&' '& Now() & RTrim(' I''m proud of you ')) FROM example1");

// Domain aggregate functions:
ResultSet rs2 = st.executeQuery("select id, DCount('*','t234','1=1') from t234");

More complete examples of access functions implementation are shown in the net.ucanaccess.test.FunctionsTest JUnit test suite.
The following functions are already implemented:

ASC, ATN, CBOOL, CCUR, CDATE, CDBL, CDEC, CINT, CLONG, CSIGN, CSTR, CVAR, DATEADD, DATEDIFF, DATEPART, DATE, DATESERIAL, DATEVALUE, FIX, FORMAT, IIF, INSTR, INSTRREV, ISDATE, ISNUMERIC, INT, IsNull, LEN, MID, MONTHNAME, NOW, NZ, PARTITION, SIGN, SPACE, SQR, STR,, STRING, STRCOMP, STRCONV, STRREVERSE, SWITCH, RND, TIME, TIMESERIAL, VAL, WEEKDAY, WEEKDAYNAME

Aggregate and Domain Functions:

FIRST, LAST, DCOUNT, DAVG, DSUM, DMAX, DMIN, DFIRST, DLAST, DLOOKUP

Financial Functions:

MT, NPER, IPMT, PPMT, RATE, PV, FV, DDB, SYD, SLN

Also you can use the following functions from the hsqldb implementation:

COS, SIN, LTRIM, RTRIM, UCASE, LCASE

Aggregate Functions:

COUNT, AVG, SUM, MAX, MIN, STDEV, STDEVP, VAR, VARP

User-defined Functions

Step 1: implementation of a new function:

public static class XXX {
    @FunctionType(functionName = "justconcat", argumentTypes = {AccessType.TEXT, AccessType.TEXT}, returnType = AccessType.TEXT)
    public static String concat(String _s1, String _s2) {
        return _s1 + " >>>>" + _s2;
    }
}

Step 2: Registration:

UcanaccessConnection uc=(UcanaccessConnection) this.ucaConn;
uc.addFunctions(XXX.class);

Step 3: Trying your new function:

ResultSet rs=st.executeQuery("SELECT justConcat(descr,''&now()) FROM example1");

Using Criteria in LIKE Clause

ResultSet rs = st.executeQuery("SELECT descr FROM example2 WHERE descr LIKE 'P%'");
// access * jolly
rs = st.executeQuery("SELECT descr FROM example2 WHERE descr LIKE 'P*'");
// number and interval patterns
rs = st.executeQuery("SELECT descr FROM example2 WHERE descr LIKE 'P[A-F]###'");
// number pattern
rs = st.executeQuery("SELECT descr FROM example2 WHERE descr LIKE 'C#V##'");

Limit and offset SQL pagination

rs = st.executeQuery("SELECT * FROM example2 order by id desc LIMIT 5 OFFSET 1");
rs = st.executeQuery("SELECT TOP 10 * FROM example2 order by id");

Performing transactions

conn.setAutoCommit(false);
st = this.ucaConn.createStatement();
st.executeUpdate("UPDATE example4 SET descr='Lugo di Romagna'");
st.execute("INSERT INTO example4 (ID, descr) VALUES(5,'DALLAS')");
conn.commit();

Using updatable ResultSet

PreparedStatement ps = super.ucanaccess.prepareStatement(
    "SELECT * FROM T1", ResultSet.TYPE_FORWARD_ONLY, ResultSet.CONCUR_UPDATABLE, ResultSet.CLOSE_CURSORS_AT_COMMIT);
rs = ps.executeQuery();
rs.next();
rs.updateString(2, "show must go off");
rs.updateRow();

Working with date type

st.execute("INSERT INTO example1 (descr, number, date0) "
    + "VALUES(\"Show must go up and down\" ,-113.55446, #11/22/2003 10:42:58 PM#)");

Working with OLE type

InputStream isDB = rs.getBinaryStream("OleColumn");
File file = new File("mypic.jpg");
OutputStream outFile = new FileOutputStream(file);
byte[] ba = new byte[4096];
while ((len = isDB.read(ba)) != -1) {
    outFile.write(ba, 0, len);
}
out.flush();
out.close();
System.out.println("mypic.jpg was created in " + file.getAbsolutePath());

About ' and " escaping

Both ' and " are valid string delimiters.
So the following SQL statements are correct:

UPDATE TABLE1 SET SURN='D''Ambrogio';(value saved=D'Ambrogio)

UPDATE TABLE1 SET SURN="""D'Ambrogio""";(value saved="D'Ambrogio")

Working with Complex Types

...
PreparedStatement ps = conn.prepareStatement("INSERT INTO TABLE1(ID , MEMO_DATA , APPEND_MEMO_DATA , MULTI_VALUE_DATA , ATTACH_DATA) VALUES (?,?,?,?,?)");
ps.setString(1, "row12");
ps.setString(2, "ciao");
ps.setString(3, "to version");
SingleValue[] svs = new SingleValue[] {new SingleValue("ccc16"), new SingleValue("ccc24")};
// Array of net.ucanaccess.complex.SingleValue

ps.setObject(4, svs);
Attachment[] atcs =
    new Attachment[] {new Attachment(null, "ccc.txt", "txt", "ddddd ddd".getBytes(), new Date(), null), new Attachment(null, "ccczz.txt", "txt", "ddddd zzddd".getBytes(), new Date(), null)};
// Array of net.ucanaccess.complex.Attachment

ps.setObject(5, atcs);
ps.execute();
...

ps = conn.prepareStatement("UPDATE TABLE1 SET APPEND_MEMO_DATA='THE CAT' ");
// APPEND_MEMO_DATA is an append only column: a new net.ucanaccess.complex.Version will be added to the version array

ps.execute();
...

// insert existing file as an attachment
// (note that the parameter value is an Attachment *array*, even for a single attachment)
String attachmentPath = "C:/Users/Gord/Documents/sample.pdf";
byte[] attachmentData = java.nio.file.Files.readAllBytes(Paths.get(attachmentPath));
ps = super.ucanaccess.prepareStatement("UPDATE TABLE1 SET ATTACH_DATA=?");
Attachment[] attachmentArray = new Attachment[] {
    new Attachment(null, "sample.pdf", "pdf", attachmentData, new java.util.Date(), null)
};
ps.setObject(1, attachmentArray);
ps.executeUpdate();

// you cannot use = operator here: use the Equals or the EqualsIgnoreOrder functions instead
ps = conn.prepareStatement("SELECT * FROM Table1 WHERE Equals(ATTACH_DATA,?)");
ps.setObject(1, atc);
ResultSet rs = ps.executeQuery();
while (rs.next()) {
    System.out.println(rs.getObject("ATTACH_DATA"));
    // rs.getObject("ATTACH_DATA") will return an array of net.ucanaccess.complex.Attachment
}
...

Filtering on Complex Type Columns (since v2.0.9)

The equality operator (=) can't be used on complex type columns, use the following functions instead.

- Equals. It returns true if the two specified arrays of SingleValue, Attachment or Version are equal to one another, false otherwise. In other words they are equal if all corresponding pairs of elements in the two arrays are equal.

//true for all records whose MULTI_VALUE_COLUMN value equals [value1,value2]
...
PreparedStatement ps = conn.prepareStatement("SELECT * FROM TABLE1 WHERE Equals(MULTI_VALUE_COLUMN,?)");
ps.setObject(1, SingleValue.multipleValue("value1", "value2"));
ResultSet rs = ps.executeQuery();
...

- EqualsIgnoreOrder. It returns true if the two specified arrays of SingleValue, Attachment or Version are equal to one another regardless the order, false otherwise.

//true for all records whose MULTI_VALUE_COLUMN value equals [value1,value2] or [value2,value1]
...
PreparedStatement ps = conn.prepareStatement("SELECT * FROM TABLE1 WHERE EqualsIgnoreOrder(MULTI_VALUE_COLUMN,?)");
ps.setObject(1, SingleValue.multipleValue("value1", "value2"));
ResultSet rs = ps.executeQuery();
...

- Contains. It returns true if the Array of SingleValue, Attachment or Version(column value) passed as first argument contains all the element of the Array passed as second argument.

// true for all records whose MULTI_VALUE_COLUMN value contains both value1 and value2
...
PreparedStatement ps = conn.prepareStatement("SELECT * FROM TABLE1 WHERE Contains(MULTI_VALUE_COLUMN,?) ");
ps.setObject(1, SingleValue.multipleValue("value1", "value3"));
ResultSet rs = ps.executeQuery();
...

Table renaming (since v4.0.0)

st.execute("ALTER TABLE [My old name] RENAME TO [My new name]");

Add new Column to Existing Table (since v4.0.0)

st.execute("ALTER TABLE xxx ADD COLUMN yyy TEXT");

st.execute("ALTER TABLE zzz ADD COLUMN kkk DATETIME NOT NULL DEFAULT now()");

st.execute("ALTER TABLE [222 crazy name] ADD COLUMN [another crazy name] numeric (23,6) default 13.031955 not null");

Add new Index to Existing Table (since v4.0.0)

st.execute("CREATE unique INDEX [index name] on [table name] (a ASC,c ASC )");

st.execute("CREATE INDEX [index name] on bbb (a ASC,c ASC )");

Add Primary Key to Existing Table (since v4.0.0)

st.execute("ALTER TABLE xxx ADD PRIMARY KEY (column1,column2)");

Foreign Key creation (since v4.0.0)

st.execute("ALTER TABLE x ADD CONSTRAINT constr FOREIGN KEY (colx1,colx2) REFERENCES y (coly1, coly2) ON DELETE CASCADE");
// or
st.execute("ALTER TABLE x ADD CONSTRAINT constr FOREIGN KEY (colx1,colx2) REFERENCES y (coly1, coly2) ON DELETE SET NULL");

Counters handling (since v3.0.0)

st.execute("DISABLE AUTOINCREMENT ON TABLE_NAME");
st.execute("ENABLE AUTOINCREMENT ON TABLE_NAME");

Using the UCanAccess command-line console

Execute console.bat (Windows) or console.sh (Linux/Unix) in the distribution to run the command-line tool (main class: net.ucanaccess.console.Main). It will prompt you to enter the path to the Access DB file. Once it reads in the database file, it will print out a prompt. You can enter SQL queries or commands at this prompt. All queries and commands end with a semicolon (";").

A SQL query looks like this: UCanAccess>SELECT * FROM License;

You can export the result of the most recent SQL query to a CSV file using the export command: UCanAccess>export License.csv;

The export command supports a number of flags, which are described by the --help flag:

UCanAccess>export --help;
Usage: export [--help] [--bom] [-d <delimiter>] [-t <table>] [--big_query_schema <pathToSchemaFile>] [--newlines] <pathToCsv>;
Export the most recent SQL query to the given <pathToCsv> file.
  -d <delimiter> Set the CSV column delimiter (default: ';').
  -t <table>     Output the <table> instead of the previous query.
  --big_query_schema <schemaFile>  Output the BigQuery schema to <schemaFile>.
  --bom          Output the UTF-8 byte order mark.
  --newlines     Preserve embedded newlines (\r, \n).
  --help         Print this help message.
Single (') or double (") quoted strings are supported.
Backslash (\) escaping (e.g. \n, \t) is enabled within quotes.
Use two backslashes (\\) to insert one backslash within quotes (e.g. "c:\\temp\\newfile.csv").

-d <delimiter> By default the delimiter between columns in the CSV file is the semicolon (;) for historical reasons. If you want to change this to a comma, use this flag like this: UCanAccess>export -d , License.csv;

-t <table> By default the export command uses the result set of the previous SQL command. This flag sends the given <table> to the CSV file by executing the SQL query SELECT * FROM [table]. For example, UCanAccess>export -t License License.csv;

-big_query_schema <schemaFile> This flag generates the JSON formatted schema file which contains the data type information (e.g. "string", "integer") of each column which are required by Google BigQuery. This schema file can be used by the BigQuery load tool. For example, UCanAccess>export -d , -t License --big_query_schema License.schema License.csv; will generate two files, License.csv and License.schema. These can be imported into Google BigQuery using the bq load command like this: $ bq load --skip_leading_rows=1 mydataset.License License.csv License.schema

--bom The CSV file will be encoded in UTF-8 format. Microsoft Excel does not support UTF-8 encoding unless the file contains a Byte Order Mark. This flag produces that byte order mark (EF BB BF). UCanAccess>export --bom -t License License.csv;

--newlines By default any embedded newlines (\n or \r, in other words, ASCII characters 0x0A and 0x0D respectively) are converted into a space character in the CSV file. This is because many CSV readers are not able to read multi-line records. This flag preserves newline characters by enclosing them in double-quote characters. UCanAccess>export --newlines -t License License.csv; Microsoft Excel supports newline characters within quotes. Google BigQuery requires the --allow_quoted_newlines flag to be given, like this: $ bq load --allow_quoted_newlines --skip_leading_rows=1 mydataset.License License.csv License.schema

Quotes The export command supports single or double quotes in the arguments, which allows table names and file names to contain embedded spaces and other special characters. For example, the command UCanAccess>export -d '\t' -t "License and Address" 'License and Address.csv'; exports the table named "License and Address" to a file named "License and Address.csv", using the TAB character as a delimiter between columns.

Within the quotes, backslash escaping of the following special characters are supported:

'\a' - bell (0x07)
'\b' - backspace (0x08)
'\f' - form feed (0x0C)
'\n' - newline (0x0A)
'\r' - carriage return (0x0D)
'\t' - tab (0x09)
'\v' - vertical tab (0x0B)
'\\' - backslash (\, 0x5C))
'\nn', '\nnn' - octal character escapes

In Windows, the backslash character is the file path separator. If we use quotes, we need to use two backslashes to represent one backslash of a Windows file path. For example the following two commands are identical: UCanAccess>export -t License c:\temp\new\License.csv; UCanAccess>export -t License "c:\\temp\\new\\License.csv";

DBeaver

DBeaver (Universal Database Manager) will automatically download and install UCanAccess as the default MS Access driver.

DBeaver web site: https://dbeaver.io/

SQLeo

UcanAccess 2.0.2 has been successfully tested with the SQLeo Visual Query Builder.

SQLeo project: https://sourceforge.net/projects/sqleo/

LibreOffice Base / OpenOffice Base

For detailed instructions on how to configure LibreOffice Base or OpenOffice Base with UCanAccess please see this question on Ask Ubuntu.

OpenOffice web site: http://www.openoffice.org
LibreOffice web site: http://www.libreoffice.org/

Using UCanAccess as NetBeans Service

Integration tested with UCanAccess 2.0.4.1. It doesn't work with previous UCanAccess versions.

1) Define a new Driver in the Netbeans "Services" tab: Services > Databases > Drivers > New Driver...

2) In the field "Driver File(s)" add "ucanaccess-x.y.z.jar" and all dependencies (all jars in the lib/ folder of the UCanAccess distribution: "hsqldb.jar", "jackcess-x.y.z.jar").

Setting the field Driver Class: net.ucanaccess.jdbc.UcanaccessDriver

3) Create a connection using the following JDBC Connection URL examples:
Windows local path: jdbc:ucanaccess://C:/Users/Public/Database1.accdb;showSchema=true

Windows UNC path: jdbc:ucanaccess:////servername/sharename/foldername/Database1.accdb;showSchema=true

Linux/Unix: jdbc:ucanaccess:///home/gord/Documents/Database1.accdb;showSchema=true (Notice that the showSchema connection property must be set to true.)

4) Now you can see your db tables listed in the PUBLIC schema.

NetBeans web site: https://netbeans.org

Squirrel SQL

For detailed instructions on how to configure Squirrel SQL with UCanAccess please see this answer on Stack Overflow.

Squirrel SQL web site: http://www.squirrelsql.org/